if you aren't familiar Dr Dre is a
dermatologist who has a passion for skin
care in a relatively recent video she
went over several myths surrounding
collagen and two of them stuck out to me
specifically gelatin better than
supplementing with collagen and should
we just Chuck the collagen supplements
if we consume enough protein both of
these are brought up often but what does
Dr Dre an expert in skin care say and
what does the science say well let's
find out the first myth is about gelatin
versus collagen the claim is often that
gelatin is just as good if not better
than collagen peptides let's hear what
Dr Dre thinks and then I'll jump in with
some studies number one myth is just eat
gelatin it's the same thing it is not
gelatin is collagen that has been
denatured and partially hydrolized
meaning it's not been broken into those
tiny little digestible peptides that's
not to say that gelatin is bad um or
that it's useless but if you are
specifically seeking to achieve the
outcomes demonstrated in the studies and
again they have their limitations but if
that's what you're looking for well
you're going to actually be missing out
if you just go with gelatin because
gelatin is not those small little
peptide fragments um it's a much they're
much larger fragments you're not going
to be it's not the same thing so you're
not going to be pursuing the same
outcome gelatin in contrast to
hydrolized collagen peptides has some
properties to it that make it desirable
namely as a food additive and that it
has the property of well jelling so yeah
that's that's an advantage of gelatin
over hydrolized peptides Dr Dre points
out that collagen peptides are
structurally different from gelatin
that's true if we lean on this
scientific review I know it says a joint
health there but it also applies to for
the face like anti- wrinkling effects in
this context the researchers point out
that gelatin is merely a denatured
protein so instead of being folded
together proteins they've been opened up
and turned into a linear poly or many
peptide chain or a a linear amino acid
chain on the other hand collagen
peptides are smaller pieces of collagen
structure that have been cut up so
instead of a long polypeptide chain the
peptides are cut into double and triple
amino acids still molecularly linked
together either way gelatin must be
effectively cut up into peptides to be
absorbed and while that does happen in
the intestinal tract via enzymes called
proteases the bioavailability or the
amount absorbed is likely a little bit
less than that of already formed cagen
peptides either one will probably work
but for slight Improvement the peptides
have a slight Advantage at least based
on the mechanisms but I doubt that it
really matters too much I think the
bigger question is related to protein
versus collagen and there's a lot of
disagreement number three myth just eat
protein just eat more animal-based
protein surely you'll be getting enough
of the amino acids that you find in
these hydrolyzed collagen supplements
just eat some tough cuts of meat like
brisket or pot roast um again it all
boils down to the fact no pun intended
so we're talking about cooking that this
is not going to actually provide you
with reliable levels of the hydrolyzed
collagen peptides is small available
digestible absorbable peptides that lead
to the presumed benefits that you are
seeking in terms of the skin you know
eating more meat is not the same thing
as pursuing Hydro collagen peptide
another myth that I hear is like well
this is all Bs because surely you're
just going to consume these peptides and
they're just going to get broken down in
your digestive tract digested just like
any other protein and absorbed into the
body they're not going to have any it's
not any different than just making sure
that you have enough protein in your
diet and that's not true either when you
eat you know peptides proteins that they
are broken down into amino acids which
are absorbed into the Sur circulation
yes that is true but also your body can
absorb peptides intact as they are
across the small intestine into the
circulation okay so the idea is that
consuming complete protein sources will
yield the same amino acids the building
blocks of proteins as collagen peptides
will this is especially the case
considering that all proteins are
cleaved into their single amino acid
form I've heard this one a lot and when
I first started my education I thought
the actually however there is excellent
evidence that is not the case in fact as
Dr Dre points out the intestine not only
absorbs single amino acids but it has
the ability to absorb D and tri peptides
like those of collagen peptides we see
that evidenced here in this study people
consume some protein and the researchers
then measured their blood levels of D
and tripeptides and as can be seen at
either dose it doesn't really matter the
specifics peptides were found in the
blood that indicates strongly that we
don't just absorb amino acids by
themselves well then if that's true then
surely protein sources could also be
absorbed as D and tri peptides and they
do however collagen peptides are unique
in that they're made up of three amino
acids stuck together so Proline Glycine
and hydroxyproline
there are some other peptides but the
backbone is always Glycine and Proline
so since complete proteins are a mixture
of different proteins there's no
reliable way of knowing if it's the
right peptides that are being created
and absorbed in addition this matters
because there's some evidence again
Illustrated in this review along with
others that these collagen peptides are
bioactive meaning that they themselves
cause changes to the collagen in our
face and well across the body
independent of the actual amino acid
makeup however it's important for me to
detail where the evidence is currently
while mechanistically we know that
collagen peptides have unique effects in
our cells there's no proof that they are
superior to protein on collagen
production by the cells because that
comparison has never been made we only
know through some moderately strong
evidence that that collagen peptides
work but the comparison in all these
studies was either against nothing or
against a placebo and none were against
other forms of protein and in muscle
research other forms of protein are
superior to collagen peptides even if we
don't know on the skin front yet so yes
it's a myth that protein is known to be
better than colagen peptides when
discussing skin and other collagen
Centric outcomes but the opposite is
also true we don't know if collagen
peptides are superior although we do
know that they work so the takeaways
here are one gelatin is likely a fine
substitute if you prefer it two collagen
peptides are effective for combating
skin wrinkling and improving skin
elasticity even if we don't know if they
will be better than protein specifically
although mechanistic research indicates
there might be an Avenue for them to
have a slight advantage and number three
Dr Dre did a great job I mean she was
spoton but then again I mean that's no
surprise coming from an expert in skin
care so I open the studies and get into
much more detail on collagen in this
video right here and otherwise if you're
interested in the factchecking of other
health influencers via the sides I have
a playlist right here I'll see you over
there
[Music]